<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>ein Blog</title>
    <id>http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/</id>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog" type="text/html"/>
    <link rel="self" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/atom.xml" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <updated>2018-05-25T08:08:04Z</updated>
    <entry>
        <title>archive.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2018/05/25/01-archive.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2018-05-25:2018/05/25/archive</id>
        <updated>2018-05-25T08:08:04Z</updated>
        <published>2018-05-25T08:08:00Z</published>
        <category term="administrativa"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>This blog is mostly kept as an archive, for the time being. My main output
now goes through my <a href="https://fnanp.in-ulm.de/microblog/">microblog site</a> -
which might be a slight misnomer because it sometimes also contains long
form articles. </p>
<p>Mainly I've switched from this static site generator ("sbe.py"), that
nobody except myself seems to use (not even its original author, which is
a bad place to be as a user) to something jekyll based.  I'm quite happy
with it. I've detailed how I use it
<a href="https://fnanp.in-ulm.de/microblog/2018/04/24/01/">here</a> and
<a href="https://fnanp.in-ulm.de/microblog/2018/04/30/02/">here</a>.</p></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>woes6.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2016/03/01/01-woes6.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2016-03-01:2016/03/01/woes6</id>
        <updated>2016-03-01T11:47:15Z</updated>
        <published>2016-03-01T11:38:42Z</published>
        <category term="computers"/><category term="networking"/><category term="android"/><category term="xmpp"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>So. One and a half years have passed since the <a href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/07/10/01-woes5.html">last</a> woes entry. What
has changed? Why did I not continue writing them? What is my thinking now?</p>
<p>Well.</p>
<p>Basically, I have given up.</p>
<p>Or rather: it turns out that anyone of my acquaintances that I can still
reach via xmpp, I can reach via IRC just as easily. All the others have
retreated to the <a href="https://www.linuxjournal.com/content/giving-silos-their-due">silos</a> (there is actually an interesting article
behind that link, not just a definition). Now of course, <a href="https://whispersystems.org">some</a>
silos are <a href="https://threema.ch">less</a> bad than <a href="https://telegram.org">ot</a><a href="https://www.whatsapp.com">hers</a>. But they're still
silos. In the case of Signal, federation is apparently possible but the
Open Whispersystems team currently doesn't allow it. I'm sure, they have a
blog post somewhere where they explain that it's better for their users
not to have it enabled. And to tell the truth, if we look at the history
of <a href="http://www.cyanogenmod.org/blog/whisperpush-secure-messaging-integration">Whisperpush</a> (i.e. the effor to integrate the Textsecure (i.e.
Signal) protocol directly into <a href="http://www.cyanogenmod.org">Cyanogenmod</a>), which was in essence a
second Signal server, it looks as they've been proven right since that was
a bit of a clusterfuck, which, in the end, left its users stranded AFAIK.</p>
<p>So, where do we go from here? Nowhere, I think. For those friends who I
can easily talk to via IRC, I do that. Others, I talk to via Signal or
Threema because it's <em>really</em> not my thing to evangelize at them at length
about how they're not being ideologically pure. So far, I've managed to
avoid being a member of any team or group that uses <a href="https://slack.com">Slack</a>. I'm told
it's more or less "IRC with like buttons and pictures". Hooray, I guess.
Also luckily, I don't seem to know anyone who wants to talk to me via
Facebook Messenger. Which I <em>would</em> flat out refuse.</p>
<p>This future sucks. I want a different one, please.</p>
<p><strong>Addendum:</strong> What I kind of wanted to say but actually forgot to write
down is: I can't really fault people for preferring one of the silo-driven
apps mentioned above given the state of client software and protocol. I
mean maybe we're slowly getting there with <a href="https://conversations.im/">conversations</a>, but IMO it's
too little, too late.</p></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>sync.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2015/07/22/01-sync.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2015-07-22:2015/07/22/sync</id>
        <updated>2015-07-22T14:40:57Z</updated>
        <published>2015-07-22T14:40:52Z</published>
        <category term="computers"/><category term="networking"/><category term="groupware"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The question of how to keep all my (important) data mostly in sync across
my devices (appointments, contacts, tasks, notes, pictures) while not
transferring said data across the computers of untrusted third parties
(aka "the cloud") is one that I worry about again and again.</p>
<p>My current solution for pictures is just to use <a href="https://rsync.samba.org/">rsync</a> since </p>
<ul>
<li>the number of pictures only grows, never gets smaller,</li>
<li>there is a somewhat decent <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=eu.kowalczuk.rsync4android">rsync app</a> for Android.</li>
</ul>
<p>Currently I'm using <a href="http://kolab.org/">kolab</a> for all the groupware-y stuff (appointments,
tasks, notes). I've used <a href="https://owncloud.org/">owncloud</a> before but somehow, I lost trust in
that project .. it seemed like its developers were more interested in
adding new features than in fixing old problems, plus the web interface
got slower and slower and slower.</p>
<p>On my phone, things are straightforward. I use caldav and carddav to
access my data via well known Android apps and everything is peachy.</p>
<p>But, the more interesting part (to me) is: I use <a href="http://www.mutt.org/">mutt</a> as my main mail
client. How to get the email-addresses from kolab into mutt? Enter
<a href="http://lostpackets.de/pycarddav/">pycarddav</a>. It downloads data from a carddav server and puts them in an
sqlite file/db and then also provides a query-tool that can generate
output in a mutt-compatible way. So far so straightforward and according
to the help-files and the findable documentation and so forth.</p>
<p>In order to find the exact address-book url a kolab-installation provides
via carddav, I was advised to "talk to my admin", since apparently it is
possible to activate an option somewhere in the admin interface for
kolab/roundcube that will allow users to have that url displayed to them.
There is an easier way, though. Just connect your webbrowser to the url
your kolab uses for carddav in general, enter your credentials and then
click around until you are in your address book .. there, there's your
url.</p>
<p>The only real problem that needed some trial-and-error to get around was
then actually <em>using</em> that url in pycardsyncer (part of pycarddav). The
error message I kept getting wasn't very helpful ("resource missing" or
something to that effect, even though the resource line was present in my
config file). Turns out, if there is a percent-sign in your carddav-url
(which there is if your username contains an @-sign), said percent-sign
has to be escaped in the config file by putting a second percent sign in
front of it (making it %%).</p>
<p>After that, pycardsyncer ran smoothly for me.</p>
<p>If it still breaks for you, there's advise out there to run it in debug
mode (-d) and this might shed some light on how/where it breaks
(candidates are e.g. problematic characters in a field in a vcard
somewhere).</p>
<p>HTH. HAND. As they say.</p></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>tlsgatling.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2015/07/21/01-tlsgatling.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2015-07-21:2015/07/21/tlsgatling</id>
        <updated>2015-07-21T10:42:07Z</updated>
        <published>2015-07-21T10:18:10Z</published>
        <category term="computers"/><category term="networking"/><category term="security"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>So. After much too long I've gotten off my butt and managed to enable
https on this here very webserver. The software in use is <a href="https://www.fefe.de/gatling/">gatling</a> by
<a href="https://www.fefe.de">fefe</a>. Still using a <a href="https://cacert.org">CAcert certificate</a>, I'm afraid, but at this
point I'm just waiting until <a href="https://letsencrypt.org/">let's encrypt</a> is operational.</p>
<p>I've used gatling since for-fucking-ever but never really looked at the
tlsgatling part because I was too lazy. Turns out, the instructions on how
to build it aren't actually part of gatling because you need to start
earlier, you need to have openssl built with <a href="https://www.fefe.de/dietlibc/">dietlibc</a> in order for
this to work. If you have <em>that</em>, the instructions in the README.tls of
gatling do work.</p>
<p>Now I just need to figure out a policy on http vs https and whether to
redirect all http connects to https or not. Probably better to do that
when I'm no longer on CAcert, though.</p></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>woes5.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/07/10/01-woes5.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2014-07-10:2014/07/10/woes5</id>
        <updated>2014-07-10T14:22:45Z</updated>
        <published>2014-07-10T14:22:42Z</published>
        <category term="computers"/><category term="networking"/><category term="android"/><category term="xmpp"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>It has recently come to my attention that
<a href="http://www.process-one.net/en/ejabberd/">ejabberd</a> has now seen the light
and <a href="https://github.com/processone/ejabberd/pull/166">included</a>
<a href="https://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0198.html">XEP-0198: Stream Management</a>
into its XMPP daemon.</p>
<p>Given this and the fact that <a href="http://web.jabber.ccc.de/">jabber.ccc.de</a> is
running the version in question, things are looking good for mobile XMPP.
At least in theory. I will do some testing and report back afterwards ..</p></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>yaxim.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/01/30/01-yaxim.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2014-01-30:2014/01/30/01-yaxim</id>
        <updated>2014-01-30T21:06:22Z</updated>
        <published>2014-01-30T21:06:20Z</published>
        <category term="networking"/><category term="android"/><category term="computers"/><category term="xmpp"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Also, adding to my last post, <a href="https://yaxim.org">yaxim</a> is now officially updated to
support XEP-0198.</p></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>op-co.de.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/01/29/01-op-co.de.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2014-01-29:2014/01/29/op-co.de</id>
        <updated>2014-01-31T10:41:11Z</updated>
        <published>2014-01-29T14:41:25Z</published>
        <category term="computers"/><category term="networking"/><category term="android"/><category term="xmpp"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Over at <a href="http://op-co.de/">op-co.de</a>, the author of the <a href="https://yaxim.org/">yaxim</a> messenger does a much
more complete <a href="http://op-co.de/blog/posts/mobile_xmpp_in_2014/">analysis</a> of the current situation of mobile XMPP.</p>
<p>TLDR: it's even worse. Enjoy ;)</p></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>woes4.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/01/21/01-woes4.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2014-01-21:2014/01/21/woes4</id>
        <updated>2014-01-21T23:05:47Z</updated>
        <published>2014-01-21T22:39:33Z</published>
        <category term="computers"/><category term="networking"/><category term="android"/><category term="xmpp"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>So. Another day, another entry.</p>
<p>This is a further point in my <a href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/tags/xmpp.html">ongoing quest</a> to get to the bottom
of XMPP on mobile devices and why it sucks and how to make it better. This
saga started <a href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/01/16/01-woes.html">here</a>.</p>
<h1>sending clients</h1>
<p>I've looked at some more client software for the sending side (i.e. Linux
based, not for Android).</p>
<ul>
<li>everything based on <a href="https://developer.pidgin.im/wiki/WhatIsLibpurple">libpurple</a></li>
<li><a href="http://mcabber.com">mcabber</a></li>
</ul>
<h2>libpurple</h2>
<p><a href="https://developer.pidgin.im/wiki/WhatIsLibpurple">libpurple</a> is the basis of <a href="https://developer.pidgin.im">pidgin</a>, which I've already talked about
in the <a href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/01/16/01-woes.html">first entry</a> of this series. There are some other clients that
use libpurple for communication, among them finch (also by the pidgin
developers) or <a href="http://www.centerim.org/index.php/Main_Page">centerim</a>.</p>
<p>Since libpurple neither shows the error messages described in the <a href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/01/16/01-woes.html">first
entry</a> nor supports <a href="https://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0184.html">XEP-0184</a> (message delivery receipts), none of
the clients based on libpurple do either.</p>
<p>There <em>is</em> an unofficial plugin for <a href="https://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0184.html">XEP-0184</a> on the <a href="https://developer.pidgin.im/ticket/6940">pidgin
bugtracker</a>, with no word on whether it'll ever be officially included
into <a href="https://developer.pidgin.im">pidgin</a>.</p>
<h2>mcabber</h2>
<p><a href="http://mcabber.com">mcabber</a> is a console client and is, as far as I can tell, the bestest
greatest coolest most awesome. It shows the error messages. It supports
<a href="https://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0184.html">XEP-0184</a>. It supports <a href="https://otr.cypherpunks.ca/">OTR</a>. And, in contrast to some other clients,
not just as a list on a webpage but this shit actually works. Wow. Mcabber
is great, w00h00 .. and so forth. If you need a console client, use this
one.</p>
<h1>more servers</h1>
<p>This time, I'm looking at "the other" xmpp daemons out there. So what have
we got:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.igniterealtime.org/projects/openfire/">openfire</a></li>
<li><a href="https://jabberd.org/">jabberd</a></li>
<li><a href="http://jabberd2.org/">jabberd2</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.lightwitch.org/metronome">metronome</a> (based on prosody)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.isode.com/products/m-link.html">isode m-link</a></li>
</ul>
<p>(also I'm sure I forgot some).</p>
<h2>openfire</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.igniterealtime.org/projects/openfire/">openfire</a> is Java based and Open Source (Apache License). It does not
support <a href="https://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0198.html">XEP-0198</a>. There is a feature request about it on the <a href="http://issues.igniterealtime.org/browse/OF-446">openfire
bugtracker</a> which received attention from users but will,
apparently, not be implemented soon due to manpower issues.</p>
<h2>jabberd</h2>
<p><a href="https://jabberd.org/">jabberd</a> does, to the best of my knowledge, not implement <a href="https://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0198.html">XEP-0198</a>.
I haven't found a clean list of "here are the standards we support", but
there is a <a href="https://jabberd.org/codedoc/files.html">list of files</a> with explanations that contains
<em>some</em> XEPs but no this one. The <a href="https://bugzilla.jabberd.org/">bugtracker</a> seems to be
unreachable. </p>
<h2>jabberd2</h2>
<p><a href="http://jabberd2.org/">jabberd2</a> is a separate project from <a href="https://jabberd.org/">jabberd</a>. They do list
<a href="https://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0198.html">XEP-0198</a> on their "supported protocols" <a href="https://github.com/jabberd2/jabberd2/blob/master/README.protocol">page</a> <em>but</em>
they mean version 0.3 of the XEP (<a href="https://www.mail-archive.com/jabberd2@lists.xiaoka.com/msg01653.html">see here</a>) which is from
2007 and <em>quite</em> out of date and from what I know not compatible with
modern implementations and didn't implement most of the features that this
standard does nowadays.</p>
<h2>metronome</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.lightwitch.org/metronome">metronome</a> is a fork of <a href="http://prosody.im/">prosody</a> and claims to support <a href="https://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0198.html">XEP-0198</a>.
Since it works in prosody, I kinda assume it also works in metronome.</p>
<h2>isode m-link</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.isode.com/products/m-link.html">isode m-link</a> is, apparently, commercial software and I don't know and
can't test (cf "commercial") whether it supports <a href="https://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0198.html">XEP-0198</a> and if yes
how well it does. Does anyone know? Please tell me, I'll amend this
section.</p>
<p><em>UPDATE</em><br/>
an eagle-eyed reader (dx on #bitlbee) pointed me to a <a href="http://www.isode.com/products/m-link-standards.html">feature
list</a> on its webpage, which does include XEP-0198.</p></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>more.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/01/20/01-more.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2014-01-20:2014/01/20/more</id>
        <updated>2014-01-20T10:31:13Z</updated>
        <published>2014-01-20T10:31:04Z</published>
        <category term="administrativa"/><category term="xmpp"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>A quick note: I am currently slightly leisure-time-challenged so it'll
take at least untill Tuesday evening for the next post in the xmpp-series
to show up. Working on a test of the new version of Chatsecure, more
sending client software (mcabber) as well as a look at the other server
software out there. Plus, a different kind of network problem than the one
analyzed so far.</p></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>woes3.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/01/18/02-woes3.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2014-01-18:2014/01/18/woes3</id>
        <updated>2014-01-18T17:38:26Z</updated>
        <published>2014-01-18T17:38:23Z</published>
        <category term="computers"/><category term="networking"/><category term="android"/><category term="xmpp"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>A continuation of <a href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/01/16/01-woes.html">this</a> and <a href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/01/18/01-woes2.html">that</a>.</p>
<p>I've now also tried out <a href="http://gajim.org">gajim</a> as the sending client. In contrast to
psi and pidgin, this one works nicely in that it informs users of problems
with delivery and also of the final error message from the server. So well
done gajim!</p></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>woes2.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/01/18/01-woes2.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2014-01-18:2014/01/18/woes2</id>
        <updated>2014-01-18T17:41:44Z</updated>
        <published>2014-01-18T10:53:42Z</published>
        <category term="computers"/><category term="networking"/><category term="android"/><category term="xmpp"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>This is a followup to my previous post <a href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/01/16/01-woes.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>Things that happened since writing the post:</p>
<ul>
<li>Pidgin have now acknowledged their "not showing error stanzas" bug and
  basically replied with <a href="https://developer.pidgin.im/ticket/15864#comment:1">it's complicated</a>. The main problem
  seems to be that, like BitlBee as well, Pidgin doesn't keep a list of
  stanzas that were already sent, so the information that a certain
  message ID had an error doesn't really carry meaningful information. We
  can hope.</li>
<li>Chatsecure have <a href="https://lists.mayfirst.org/pipermail/guardian-dev/2014-January/003065.html">expressed</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/n8fr8/status/424198994638942208">dismay</a> about the timing of my post
  since they think they have fixed most of the issues I complained about
  in an update that was released right after I published my post. I'll
  certainly give the new version a trial run and share my thoughts on it
  in a few days.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/jabbercccde/status/423852561251446786">Also</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/4b73cb/status/423855231198576640">there</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/Natanji/status/424107842980020224">were</a> some reactions and discussions on twitter.
  (including <a href="https://twitter.com/g0rdin/status/424144085742407680">reference</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/g0rdin/status/424144136887734272">to</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/g0rdin/status/424229109657391105">yet</a> another ejabberd annoyance)</li>
</ul>
<p>So that's that for now. More as the story develops.</p>
<p><em>Update: I've now also looked at <a href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/01/18/02-woes3.html">gajim</a> as the sending client</em> </p></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>woes.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/01/16/01-woes.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2014-01-16:2014/01/16/woes</id>
        <updated>2014-07-10T14:31:09Z</updated>
        <published>2014-01-16T16:49:29Z</published>
        <category term="computers"/><category term="networking"/><category term="android"/><category term="xmpp"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><em>Update 7: ejabberd has <a href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/07/10/01-woes5.html">seen the light</a></em><br/>
<em>Update 6: the author of yaxim does a much more complete <a href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/01/29/01-op-co.de.html">analysis</a></em><br/>
<em>Update 5: I've looked at more sending clients and more servers
<a href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/01/21/01-woes4.html">here</a></em><br/>
<em>Update 4: Added another sending client to the list of tested software
<a href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/01/18/02-woes3.html">here</a></em><br/>
<em>Update 3: I've written a new post linking to a few reactions <a href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/01/18/01-woes2.html">here</a></em><br/>
<em>Update 2: this post has gotten a few reactions. There will be a
  followup-post soon-ish</em><br/>
<em>Update: made some more inline links to the bug reports</em></p>
<h1>Intro (what is this about)</h1>
<p>So for a long time I've had an <a href="https://xmpp.org">XMPP</a> (historically also
known as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jabber">Jabber</a>) account on
<a href="http://web.jabber.ccc.de">jabber.ccc.de</a>. There are a lot of reasons for
preferring xmpp over other protocols for instant messaging but I don't
really feel like repeating stuff that has been said a million times.</p>
<p>Anyway, long after most other people I got myself a smartphone 3 years
ago and ever since have struggled with the fact that even though in
theory, xmpp <em>should</em> be much greater than all the closed alternatives, in
reality and for mobile use it often isn't, which is why one can evangelise
all one wants, people will continue using e.g. WhatsApp not just because
of ignorance but because, sadly, it just works. </p>
<p>Now what do I mean by "it just works": It is well known that
security-wise, WhatsApp is a nightmare, but, and this is an important
point, messages reach their destination most of the time, and if they
don't, there is some way the user finds out about that.</p>
<p>The problem with the open version of mobile xmpp (I presume WhatsApp is
just some kind of modified xmpp internally) is that this isn't the case
here.</p>
<p>A scenario. Alice wants to talk to Bob. Alice might be sitting in front of
her computer or use her mobile phone, it doesn't matter, what matters is
Bob is using his mobile phone. Now if Alice sends a message and Bob loses
his network connectivity for a few seconds before receiving this message,
the message is just lost when using xmpp. This comes as a surprise to a
lot of people, since after all, xmpp is TCP/IP based, but it is still the
case, since xmpp doesn't use any confirmation mechanism. This is, afaict,
because the standard was written at a time when it was thought that the
main use would be users that are all connected to the server via short,
high-speed LANs, probably in the same building or so. Also, it takes a
while for an xmpp server to realise that one of its users has dropped off
the net, so Alice might see a that Bob has logged off .. but that will
happen up to 15 minutes <em>after</em> he actually lost connectivity.</p>
<p>Bob might come back online after a few seconds, but, this is the awful
part, neither the server nor Alice will ever know that he never received
the message that was sent while he was away (because neither even saw that
he was away). And if Bob has his mobile phone in his pocket he will also
not notice. So there might be messages before and after the lost message
that he does receive. It can become quite confusing.</p>
<p>There are extensions to the XMPP protocol which are labelled
"XEP-something" where "something" is a number. Those extensions (there are
quite a lot of them) are listed at
<a href="https://xmpp.org/xmpp-protocols/xmpp-extensions/">this link</a>. Some of those were
created explicitly with the goal of solving the problem I describe above.
The first interesting one here is <a href="https://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0184.html">XEP-0184: Message Delivery
Receipts</a> which allows clients
to tell each other "yep, got that message". But the most important one is
<a href="https://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0198.html">XEP-0198: Stream Management</a>,
which allows a client to tell the server "oh hey, I was gone for a few
seconds/minutes there, got any messages for me?"</p>
<h1>Overview of the current situation</h1>
<p>So, case closed, right? Everybody implements XEP-0198 in their software
and things are peachy!</p>
<p>Well no. Because they don't. Implement it, that is.</p>
<p>For this to work, the client (the app on the mobile phone) as well as the
server have to support XEP-0198.</p>
<h2>daemon software</h2>
<p>In the server world, the situation is:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.process-one.net/en/ejabberd/">ejabberd</a>, written in
  <a href="http://www.erlang.org">Erlang</a> claims to be the "worlds most popular
  XMPP application server". Offers its own version of "mobile support",
  but only in the non-free "Enterprise Edition". The Open Source
  "Community Edition" has neither that proprietory implementation nor
  XEP-0198. A full breakdown of the XEPs that are supported is
  <a href="http://www.process-one.net/en/ejabberd/protocols/">here</a>. There is a
  longstanding bug in the ejabberd <a href="https://support.process-one.net/browse/EJAB-532">issue
  tracker</a> that quite
  clearly shows that the developers are not interested in implementing
  this. <br/>
  Note that <a href="http://web.jabber.ccc.de">jabber.ccc.de</a> uses ejabberd.</li>
<li>There is a <a href="https://github.com/xek/ejabberd">fork</a> of ejabberd
  (presumably of the community edition) on <a href="https://github.com">github</a>,
  with the explicit purpose of adding XEP-0198 to ejabberd. The last
  development on this fork seems to have happened three years ago.</li>
<li><a href="https://prosody.im">prosody</a>, written in <a href="http://www.lua.org">Lua</a>, has
  support for XEP-0198 in a
  <a href="http://code.google.com/p/prosody-modules/wiki/mod_smacks">plugin</a> which
  implements part of the spec (namely, what is still missing is the
  possibility for the server to commit lost messages to offline storage,
  currently it only implements the "send an error if receiver is offline
  for a time longer than timeout").</li>
</ul>
<p>There are of course other jabber daemons but those are the ones I looked
at.</p>
<h2>client software</h2>
<h3>mobile clients for Android</h3>
<p>I mainly looked at clients for Android since an Android phone is what I
have access to.</p>
<p>Popular clients include</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.xabber.org/">xabber</a>. Does not support XEP-0198. There is a
  bug in the
  <a href="https://github.com/redsolution/xabber-android/issues/67">xabber-bugtracker</a>
  that doesn't have any comments from developers and isn't assigned to
  anyone.</li>
<li><a href="http://beem-project.com/">beem</a>. Does not support XEP-0198. There is a
  bug in the <a href="http://beem-project.com/issues/400">beem bugtracker</a> which
  was opened two years ago and has no activity beyond being changed from
  "bug" to "feature request" 9 months ago.</li>
<li><a href="https://guardianproject.info/apps/chatsecure/">chatsecure</a>, formerly
  known as Gibberbot, is probably the most feature-complete xmpp-app for
  Android, at least according to its specs. Supports
  <a href="https://otr.cypherpunks.ca/">OTR</a> as well as XEP-0198.</li>
<li><a href="https://yaxim.org">yaxim</a> supports XEP-0198 as well as XEP-0184.</li>
</ul>
<h3>linux clients</h3>
<p>There isn't really any necessity for a client that doesn't use mobile
networking or is stationary to implement XEP-0198, but that doesn't mean
that we can ignore those clients. According to XEP-0198, if a server
detects that a client is gone for good, it may react "by either returning
an error to the sender or committing the stanza to offline storage."</p>
<p>That "error to the sender" is a stanza with the same message-ID as the
original message, no content and is of type="error". One would presume
that a client receiving such an error message would endeavour to inform
its user but alas, this is not the case. I looked at the following
clients:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://bitlbee.org">BitlBee</a> is a gateway that translates various chat
  protocols (including XMPP) to IRC, thereby allowing the user to have
  them all in his/her favourite IRC client.</li>
<li><a href="http://psi-im.org/">psi</a> pure XMPP client, graphical.</li>
<li><a href="http://pidgin.im/">pidgin</a> Multi-IM client, graphical.</li>
</ul>
<h1>my findings</h1>
<p>I used my own ARCH Linux server and installed prosody and the XEP-0198
plugin on it. It has to be noted that the
<a href="http://code.google.com/p/prosody-modules/wiki/mod_smacks">mod_smacks</a>-plugin
currently in <a href="http://aur.archlinux.org">AUR</a> is not the current one and
therefore doesn't work. Installing it by hand is easy, since it's just one
file.  Then I used one account for the desktop clients and one for the
mobile clients to test scenarios of loss of connectivity for different
lengths of time, as well as mobile to mobile chats.</p>
<p>I simulated loss of connectivity on the phone by first deactivating mobile
networking (to take away the fallback option) and then turning off the
wifi. What should happen is that when one re-enables wifi after a short
time, the client should tell the server that he's back from an outage and
should receive queued messages. A remote chat party shouldn't see the
disconnect/reconnect. When the outage goes on for longer (in my tests at
least 10 minutes, up to 15 minutes), the server realises something is
amiss and starts his countdown. After the countdown is over (5 minutes
default), the sender receives an error message from the server.</p>
<h2>sending side</h2>
<p>Of the senders tested (Bitlbee, Psi, Pidgin, Yaxim for mobile to mobile),
initially <em>none</em> showed the error message to the user (see bug reports
below). </p>
<p>Yaxim fixed that <a href="https://github.com/pfleidi/yaxim/issues/108">bug</a> on the same day and now shows a red cross
over the message concerned as well as an extra message in the chat stream
that reads "recipient-unavailable(-1)" and has a red background.</p>
<p>BitlBee acknowledged the <a href="http://bugs.bitlbee.org/bitlbee/ticket/1114">bug</a> on IRC and discussed how they
might fix it.  Bitlbee has the problem that up untill now it doesn't
generate message IDs and it is (AFAIK) not easy to change the way a line
that has already been written to the IRC client is displayed after the
fact. The discussion went in the direction of basically putting a
timestamp into the message-ID, thereby allowing a message of the type
"your message from 'time' could not be delivered" to be generated upon
error. Since at least one developer has tested the problem together with
me I presume the bug is being worked upon.</p>
<p>Psi have so far not reacted to the <a href="https://github.com/psi-im/psi/issues/104">bug report</a>.</p>
<p>Pidgin have so far not reacted to the <a href="https://developer.pidgin.im/ticket/15864">bug report</a>.</p>
<h2>server side</h2>
<p>Prosody implements XEP-0198 correctly, as far as I can see. Nevertheless,
I would prefer if the second option ("or committing the stanza to offline
storage") were available as well since that would increase comfort for the
user (no need to resend messages). After discussion in the chat with
Prosody developers, I filed a <a href="http://code.google.com/p/lxmppd/issues/detail?id=383">wishlist-bug</a> for this.</p>
<h2>receiving side</h2>
<p>Yaxim works as advertised (after fixing the <a href="https://github.com/pfleidi/yaxim/issues/108">bug</a> ). The version
that incorporates these bug fixes should make its way to the Play Store
"later this week".</p>
<p>Chatsecure works as advertised some of the time. And then it doesn't. And
then it has trouble reconnecting. And then it takes 5 minutes to
reconnect. And then it sometimes doesn't see contacts as online even
though they clearly are and nothing can make it see the error of its ways.
So even though on paper it should be the best client out there, it made my
blood boil with anger ...</p>
<p>Xabber just plain doesn't support XEP-0198 so no point complaining about
it losing messages. At least it quickly reconnects after connection loss.</p>
<p>Beem is extremely bad in that it not only fails to support XEP-0198, a
loss of connectivity also causes it to display an error message and quit,
not reconnecting automatically. So unless the user intervenes <em>every</em>
<em>single</em> <em>time</em> that connectivity is lost, it won't work at all.</p>
<h1>Conclusion</h1>
<p>For now, Yaxim seems to be the best client out there (but be very aware
that it doesn't encrypt your messages end-to-end, so unless you trust all
the servers in between yourself and the recipient to correctly implement
encryption and not store your messages, treat it as unsafe for sensitive
content!). If it supported OTR as well, it would be perfect. The yaxim
bugtracker has a <a href="https://github.com/pfleidi/yaxim/issues/82">bug</a> about
OTR and <a href="https://github.com/pfleidi/yaxim/issues/83">another one</a> about
AGP.</p>
<p>Prosody as server works as advertised. If you don't want to install one
yourself, Yaxim offers an open Prosody server that supports XEP-0198 at
<a href="http://yaxim.org/yax.im/">yax.im</a>.</p>
<p>Chatsecure <em>could</em> be great if they manage to fix all the annoyances
detailed above.</p>
<p>Xabber is no contender unless it implements XEP-0198. Same for Beem.</p>
<p>I did not investigate the situation for iPhones since I don't own or have
access to an iPhone. I would be happy to hear about it though.</p>
<h1>bugs found and reported during this investigation</h1>
<ul>
<li>Yaxim: <a href="https://github.com/pfleidi/yaxim/issues/108">error stanzas are not handled correctly</a> fixed within
  the same day, maximum respect!</li>
<li>BitlBee: <a href="http://bugs.bitlbee.org/bitlbee/ticket/1114">XMPP: bitlbee receives but does not display stanzas of type
  "error"</a></li>
<li>BitlBee: <a href="http://bugs.bitlbee.org/bitlbee/ticket/1111">Opportunistic OTR tries to establish an OTR session with
  xmlconsole</a> (this one was triggered due to my investigation)</li>
<li>psi: <a href="https://github.com/psi-im/psi/issues/104">error stanzas not handled correctly (not shown to users)</a></li>
<li>Pidgin: <a href="https://developer.pidgin.im/ticket/15864">error stanzas not handled correctly (not shown to
  users)</a></li>
<li>Prosody: <a href="http://code.google.com/p/lxmppd/issues/detail?id=383">XEP-0198, also implement the "committing the stanza for
  offline storage" variant</a></li>
</ul>
<h1>texts and people that had an influence on this post</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://op-co.de/blog/posts/XEP-0198/">Here</a> is a great explanation on why
  XEP-0198 is needed.</li>
<li>people in the #yaxim channel on <a href="http://irc.freenode.net">freenode</a>
  were very responsive and helpful.</li>
<li>people in the #bitlbee channel on <a href="http://oftc.net">oftc</a> were very
  responsive and helpful as well as delightfully snarky.</li>
<li>people in the prosody community chat (see
  <a href="https://prosody.im/discuss#chatroom">here</a>) were very responsive and
  helpful.</li>
<li>Peter Schwindt, on Twitter as <a href="https://twitter.com/vautee">@vautee</a>,
  admin of <a href="http://web.jabber.ccc.de">jabber.ccc.de</a>, has been discussing
  this issue with me for quite some time now and had great influence on me
  finally deciding to sit down and actually do some real tests besides
  complaining that "things don't work".</li>
</ul></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>arp3.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2014/01/07/01-arp3.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2014-01-07:2014/01/07/arp3</id>
        <updated>2014-01-07T23:46:53Z</updated>
        <published>2014-01-07T23:44:54Z</published>
        <category term="computers"/><category term="networking"/><category term="android"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>An Update to the saga that started
<a href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2013/06/10/01-arp.html">here</a>  and continued
<a href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2013/06/11/01-arp2.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>Now, the phone (a Motorola Droid 4) is running
<a href="http://www.cyanogenmod.org">Cyanogenmod</a>, to be precise the "stable"
version for this phone, which is 10.1.3, meaning Android 4.2.2. </p>
<p>And I am still seeing the problem described in my earlier posts, namely
that an arp entry for a host that can be reached locally is not removed
from the arp table when the phone leaves the network for which this is
true.</p>
<p>Again, the scenario:</p>
<p>Phone is online in wifi A, host X is in the same network and can be
reached without passing through a router.</p>
<p>Phone is moved to another location, where wifi B (no relation with A) is
available, so phone connects to that. Phone is now unable to reach host X
as phone believes host X to <em>still</em> be a locally reachable host but
offline or invalid or whatever. When turning off the wifi (i.e. using 3G
instead), the host becomes reachable (as the arp table is specific for
each network interface). A reboot clears the arp table and makes normal
networking possible again.</p>
<p>As far as I understand the issue, this is not correct behaviour.</p></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>finnegan.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2013/09/28/01-finnegan.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2013-09-28:2013/09/28/finnegan</id>
        <updated>2013-09-28T17:18:42Z</updated>
        <published>2013-09-28T17:09:35Z</published>
        <category term="literature"/><category term="art"/><category term="language"/>
        <author>
            <name>chrissi</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>[Blog owners note: Hosting an essay about Finnegans Wake by best friend
<a href="https://twitter.com/weird_prophet">@weird_prophet</a>, who also blogs at
<a href="http://phoenixdreaming.wordpress.com">http://phoenixdreaming.wordpress.com</a> but felt that it didn't really fit in
with her regular content there. I said anything fits here. A pdf of this essay
can be downloaded
<a href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/temp/Finnegan_paper_revision_AAA.pdf">here</a>.
For your online reading pleasure, it is also included below. Note that the
formatting of the References section might be a bit wonky, I didn't find a
good way to do that in
<a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">markdown</a>. Anyway, here goes:]</p>
<h1><em>Finnegans Wake</em>: "The Ant and the Grasshopper"</h1>
<h2>A (Divine) Journey into Day (and Out of Time)</h2>
<p>Christina Scholz</p>
<p>James Joyce’s <em>Finnegans Wake</em> is very much a novel about language, and about
what language can perform. It is at the same time representing reality and
presenting language (and the various functions of language). If you take a look
at Joyce’s books in a chronological order from <em>Dubliners</em> over <em>A Portrait of the
Artist as a Young Man</em> and <em>Ulysses</em> to <em>Finnegans Wake</em>, there is a distinct shift
from a realist world-making to a language-oriented text-making. Joyce achieves
this by use of generators (cf. Mahler 2010: 109) - recombining elements or even
words from different languages, resulting in words that, when being read,
through certain patterns, similarities and free association, produce other
words (cf. Freudian slips, or, as discussed later on, so-called ‘mondegreens’).</p>
<p>Through the medium of (highly programmatic) language and text-making, Joyce
produces (rather than reproduces) the world, the city of Dublin, a set of
archetypical (and thus constantly shifting, metamorphosing) characters –
including allusions to, and connections with, the whole of Western culture (at
least up to the time of his writing), and possibly even transcending it. The
text creates and re-creates itself endlessly, not even having a conventional
beginning and ending. Similarly (maybe even consequentially), there is no
‘solution’ or ‘ideal’ reading, no assumed “only way” it could have been
intended by the author. This way a ‘heretical’ text is created (cf. possible
allusions to Milton in the following interpretation of a selected passage).</p>
<p>Thus, the reader’s task is not to ‘solve’ it, but to surrender to the ‘game’
(cf. Mahler 2010: 111) and find more and more possibilities of ‘what to do with
the text’, and perhaps even in what ways the text will affect the reader (and
their approach, their ways of reading and interpreting a certain passage).
Since the language used in <em>Finnegans Wake</em> is clearly distinct from an ordinary,
everyday use of language, it is in a way related to poetry (even where the text
appears to be prose, or at least related to prose), which allows for the
assumption that the author is playing with language, and that the readers might
decode more and more of the text by playing with it as well. They are
encouraged to bring in more than just the semiotic meaning, more than just the
signified(s), to track down the constantly shifting meanings (as in metaphor,
as opposed to allegory, cf. Miéville 2011), the seemingly endless
possibilities.</p>
<p>The first effect this unusual use of language has on the reader is disturbing -
bringing to the readers’ attention that this is not an everyday text, shifting
their focus to the use and function of language rather than content, and
guiding them away from a conventional (maybe habitual) interpretation, and
method of interpretation. Klaus Reichert aptly compares this effect to
Šklovskij’s concept of estrangement or defamiliarization (Reichert 1989: 184).
The readers’ impulse is then to ‘make sense’ of the text. Any unusual text, and
especially one that seemingly opaque, containing so many neologisms,
intertextuality, etc. demands additional work (and possibly creativity) from
its readers. So what to do with this self-generating text?</p>
<p>Our usual approach in decoding a text is to translate it from the sign, the
language to its meaning: interpretation, making meaning. If we reverse this
‘game’ (cf. Mahler 2010: 111ff) and, as suggested by Joyce’s creative wordplay,
go back again from the meaning to the code, to focus on language itself,
meaning is presented as material that seems to be there as material only (i.e.
language as such is foregrounded). If we as readers surrender to this game, we
are forced to consider the way language works and to think about the (usually)
hidden aspects of language that are not transparent in everyday language use.
Joyce’s use of language throws us back from a first (easy) interpretative
reading to a self-referential level of language, which slows down the reading
process (very much like reading poetry, which almost suggests itself
considering his use of alliteration, homonyms, homophones, etc), intensifies
the focus on the elements and uses of language, and in the end helps attain an
increasingly wide range of possible interpretations as more and more
associations manifest themselves.</p>
<p>In addition, it’s helpful to look for similar words in other languages, similar
names in literature, etc. Every possible layer of our culture until (at least)
Joyce’s time is referred to throughout the book – thus a never-ending text, and
an encyclopaedia of culture, a ‘lexicon of life’ (Füger 1994: 259), is
produced. Language is revealed as a construct that at the same time creates
other (cultural, societal) constructs on a world-level. And finally, among
other things, the book is also a treatment of our concept of time. Already the
title suggests two opposite concepts of time in one space: Linear time vs.
cyclical time.</p>
<p>The following is one possible reading of a passage from <em>Finnegans Wake</em>, i.e.
the Grasshopper’s ballad from “The Ant and the Grasshopper” in Book III (Joyce.
<em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 418f).</p>
<h2>1. Some preliminary questions</h2>
<h3>Why the ballad from "The Ant and the Grasshopper"? What kind of reading?</h3>
<p>The ballad of “The Ant and the Grasshopper” is a piece of poetry contained in a
longer prose chapter. This makes it one of many breaks in form and style, and
it also shows the necessity of a different reading approach. When reading
poetry, one has to slow down and pay more attention to elements that feature in
prose texts to a lesser degree, if at all, e.g. sounds, alliteration, rhythm /
metre, alternative meanings (through the use of generators, but also through
literary, historical or cultural context, or free association). Atmosphere
seems to be as important as context. Besides, the passage is a ballad, recited
or probably sung by the character of the Grasshopper (or Gracehoper, another
transformation of Shem the penman) to the character of the Ant (alternatively
Ondt, referring to Shaun the postman), so it is very closely related to any
kind of song – and once again reminiscent of the ballad of “Finnegan's Wake”
and the whole topic of birth and re-birth and cycles within cycles.</p>
<h3>Why is this passage worthwhile? Where is it?</h3>
<p>The fable of the Ant and the Grasshopper is contained in what is known as Book
III of <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: The Book of the People. The material of Book III is
largely the dream of Mr. Earwicker between the late hour of his arrival in bed
and the first crack of dawn (Campbell 1959: 256). Its main figure is Shawn the
Postman, who is envisioned as a great man of the future, carrying forward the
tradition of his ancestors and winning with ease the battles lost by his father
(ibid). But despite his heroic deeds, Shawn is not depicted as a hero: he is
only reluctantly accepted by the people, who after his moment of fruitless
triumph sit over him in judgement (Campbell 1959: 256f).</p>
<p>In Chapter I (“Shaun before the People”), he gives a speech in front of ‘the
people’ (i.e. the 29 maidens already encountered in an earlier chapter) to
convince them that he is more meritorious than his brother Shem. In the course
of his speech he tells them the fable of the Ant and the Grasshopper,
transformed here to the Ondt and the Gracehoper, to illustrate his arguments.</p>
<p>Chapter II (“Jaun [Don Juan] &amp; Iseult”) and Chapter III (“Yawn Recumbent” [the
inquest]) are also part of HCE’s dreams, and Chapter IV (“HCE and ALP in their
bed”) leads back to HCE and ALP in their bed leading up to the dawn of a new
day.</p>
<p>The constant transformations of characters and situations and the underlying
dream logic provide an interesting starting-point for various readings that
differ from everyday prose interpretations. One could argue that they even
justify going off on a tangent and following up ‘clues’ provided by misreadings
or associations that might seem far-fetched at first. </p>
<h3>What happens? What mechanisms are at work?</h3>
<p>The fable of the Ant and the Grasshopper (Joyce, <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 263ff) is
based on Aesop's fable of the same title. The metrical foot used in the
Grasshopper's (or Gracehoper's) song is an anapaest, a Greek metre, which
brings the original fable to mind. Simultaneously it is reminiscent of the
ballad of “Finnegan’s Wake”, especially since it takes up the theme of death
and life (or death and rebirth, according to whether it is seen from a
perspective using the concept of linear time, or one using the concept of
cyclical time – both of which are repeatedly referred to in the text). Other
recurring motives are: Egyptian mythology, insects, Biblical themes, rebellion
of the son against his father (including a possible association with Milton's
Lucifer), order vs. chaos, literature, philosophy, self-references to Joyce
(and his work), and possibly even a suggestion of mysticism, the decoding of
messages, initiation.</p>
<p>Switching from an interpretative reading to one in which language itself is
foregrounded whenever the use of language suggests it brings out playful new
versions of the fable as well as an encyclopaedia of cultural and historical
references, and a seemingly never-ending scope as to possible meanings. In
addition, each re-reading of the passage will necessarily change the text and
its functions, thus re-making <em>Finnegans Wake</em> over and over again (in accordance
with its major themes, and the story of its hero, HCE).</p>
<h2>2. Reading the Gracehoper's Ballad</h2>
<p>The paragraph preceding the ballad serves as a sort of introduction and sets
the scene:</p>
<p><em>A darkener of the threshold. Haru? Orimis, capsizer of his ant-boat, sekketh
rede from Evil-it-is, lord of loaves in Amongded. Be it! So be it!</em> (Joyce.
<em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 418)</p>
<p>What is to follow seems to be a (rite of) passage, an in-between, a transition.
Possibly even an initiation. Even though <em>haru</em> means spring (the season, which
is also a sort of beginning, a transition) in Japanese, it is simultaneously
reminiscent of the Egyptian god Horus (or Heru), who is among other things god
of the sky, god of war and god of protection and appears in various forms that
might even be different deities subsumed under one name. As HerusaAset (Heru,
son of Isis), he is responsible for the pharaoh and represents both the royal
heir and the newborn sun (cf. Hill 2010). “Orimis”, with its possible reference
to Osiris (lord of the underworld, master over life and death) strengthens this
interpretation, together with the “ant-boat” and “Evil-it-is”, the name of the
rudder (cf. Ito 2002). His position as lord of the underworld is reflected
again in “Amongded”, phonetically evoking an image of this dark realm across
cultures: “among the dead”. And of course the implied father-son relationship
brings us back to HCE (Earwicker, whose name comes up as an additional
association to the insect theme that dominates this passage) and Shaun (the
narrator), the rebellious son.</p>
<p>The threshold is darkened, but at the same time, we are following HCE’s dreams
through the night towards morning, transitioning various states of order and
chaos, passing thresholds and moments that again dissolve into a fluid stream
of time. The ant-boat inevitably evokes another boat, the sun-boat, and, in
accordance with the omnipresent theme of death and rebirth, the linear journey
into night becomes a cyclical journey back into day. Finally, the invocation
“so be it!” tells us that it is starting, and we realize that we are already on
our way. The Gracehoper begins his song.</p>
<p>At the same time it is also an ending of sorts (which implies the crossing of
another threshold): “so be it” is, among other things, a translation of
ainsi-soît-il, the French for amen.</p>
<p><em>The thing pleased him andt, and andt,</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 418)</p>
<p>“The thing pleased him” immediately reminds us of the book of Genesis in the
Bible. A world is created, which is also an ongoing process (“and and and”).
´Through repetition, this ongoing process also names and re-names the character
to whom this ballad is addressed, the transformed ant: identity is assigned,
but it is always different (cf. Finnegan/HCE).</p>
<p><em>He larved and he larved on he merd such a nauses</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 418)</p>
<p>What is repeated this time? The insect’s (the ant’s but also the grasshopper’s)
first stage of development (right after its creation in the previous line): the
larva (McHugh 1980: 418). Another beginning establishes the insect theme. (Note
here that the earwick, as in Earwicker, is also an insect [cf. Ito 2002]. Even
the shifting symbols “stay in the family”.) In addition there is reference to
its origin on a meta-textual level: if we read “merd” as <em>merde</em> (McHugh 1980:
418), not only nauseating (ibid), <em>ad nauseam</em> (referring to the repetitions),
but also reminding us of Shem the penman and the ink he made from his
excretions.</p>
<p><em>The Gracehoper feared he would mixplace his fauces.</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>:
418)</p>
<p>For the first time, the alternative name Gracehoper is used, which suggests
that our narrator is a believer in God, and also a repentant sinner. “Mixplace”
tells us that things are not in their proper places; we find ourselves in a
place of chaos rather than order. “Fauces”, which according to McHugh (1980:
418) suggests the almost homonymous “forces”, might provide an additional layer
of meaning by showing us what it is that’s out of place. If the order of things
is reversed, this could refer to the rebellion of the son, or – if we go along
with the established biblical theme, the Fall of Lucifer (either in the Bible
or in Milton’s “Paradise Lost”, making the Adversary more of a hero).</p>
<p><em>I forgive you, grondt Ondt, said the Gracehoper, weeping,</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans
Wake</em>: 418)</p>
<p>The Gracehoper, trying to re-establish harmony between himself and the Ondt,
offers forgiveness. Simultaneously, through divine forgiveness, order is (for
the moment) re-established. Meanwhile, the ant has morphed into the <em>Ondt</em>, which
means “bad”, “painful” in Danish: the Gracehoper’s opposite.</p>
<p><em>For their sukes of the sakes you are safe in whose keeping.</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans
Wake</em>: 418)</p>
<p>Here Joyce uses alliterative repetition in the way of Old English ballads
(three same stresses followed by one different repetition). <em>Sukes</em> means
assistance, according to McHugh (1980: 418). At the same time “whose keeping”
could also shift to “housekeeping” in an alternative reading (ibid). Of course,
in accordance with the biblical theme, “safe in whose keeping” is also
automatically connected with God (who forgives and protects).</p>
<p><em>Teach Floh and Luse polkas, show Bienie where’s sweet</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>:
418)</p>
<p>The insect theme continues with <em>Floh</em> (“flea”), <em>Luse</em> (almost homophonous with
“louse”) and <em>Bienie</em> (Biene meaning “bee”; also connected with sweetness –
honey). There is also a hidden musical reference: “Luisa’s Polka” by Smetana
(McHugh 1980: 418).</p>
<p><em>And be sure Vespatilla fines fat ones to heat.</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 418)</p>
<p>The insect in this line is the wasp (“Vespa”; “Vespatilla”). “Be sure
Vespatilla fines fat ones to heat” completes what the previous line has begun:
everyone gets their just desserts. Everyone is judged (at the end). “Fining”
somebody (who deserves it) “to heat” also suggests the threat of hell(fire).</p>
<p><em>As I once played the piper I must now pay the count</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 418)</p>
<p>Again, something seems to be out of order: Of course the proverb that comes to
mind is “who pays the piper calls the tune”. But “play” and “pay” are too
easily confused in this line, especially since one would expect the text to say
“pay the piper”, not “play”. In fact, in my first reading of this passage, I
accidentally thought it went on, “I must now play the count” (as in <em>The Prince
and the Pauper</em>), which at first made perfect sense in the context of order
reversed. I only realized my mistake when I read it a second time. But that
does not mean that the additional meaning generated by such a misreading has to
be immediately rejected. Hugo Keiper explains this in his 2008 essay on
another, related kind of misinterpretation, the so-called mondegreen (a
mis-hearing of song lyrics): </p>
<blockquote>
<p>[M]ondegreens apparently used to be seen for a long time as some sort of
social semiotic taboo that most people left untouched (Keiper 2008: 34). </p>
</blockquote>
<p>If you reject those misinterpretations as unfounded, you
might miss another crucial aspect, i.e. <em>what they might reveal about listener’s
minds</em> (Keiper 2008: 34). What happens in these instances is that new text is
produced by the listener. Since many song lyrics (and literary texts) play with
textual ambiguities, these mondegreens may be a deliberately evoked result -
with a lot of different outcomes, depending on the listeners’, or readers’,
backgrounds  (cf. Keiper 2008:39).</p>
<blockquote>
<p>[M]ondegreens can be seen as a marvellous empirical source of actual and
everyday interpretations, or rather misinterpretations, of lyric poetry –
‘readings’ that come about quite spontaneously, that is, without the
interference of situational factors that may be artificial and distorting, such
as filling in questionnaires or answering a researcher’s questions. […] Viewed
from this perspective, mondegreens may tell us a great deal about real-life
decoding or ‘reading’ of oral texts […], with reference perhaps to some of the
mechanisms and constraints affecting the reading of poetry, and of other kinds
of literary texts. Keiper 2008:42)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Keiper stresses that the range of possible (and possibly valid) interpretations
is very wide, and that through the study of mondegreens priority is shifting
away from concepts like the ‘ideal’ listener or reader (cf. Keiper 2008: 42f).</p>
<blockquote>
<p>[They] provide strong evidence against mainstream models of lit. crit.
featuring ideal(ized) readers, who read a text exactly as it is supposedly
‘intended’ or ‘meant’ (or in any case as it 'should be ideally read’ according
to a particular critic, or following so-called critical opinion, consensus,
etc), and which claim that such readers do so availing themselves of the full
context and semiotic potential inscribed in a text. Keiper 2008:43)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Especially an ‘open’ text (cf. Eco 1977) like <em>Finnegans Wake</em> with its many
portmanteau words (cf. Füger 194: 274) and neologisms strongly suggests a wider
perspective concerning possible ‘readings’ or interpretations, as indicated
above. Thus, even misreadings can provide valuable additional insights not only
into how the text is constructed and the implicit possibilities of reading and
“decoding” it, but also into the mechanisms of the reading process itself and
the workings of the readers’ minds.  In this context, my (mis)interpretation
pointing to the recurring motive of reversed order might again justify bringing
back the theme of the rebellious son, or Milton’s Lucifer – who deems it
“[b]etter to reign in Hell, then [sic] serve in Heav'n“ (Milton. „Paradise
Lost“ 1:263). Alternatively (or additionally), the line about paying “the
count” might suggest paying one’s due – which brings back the notion of order
re-established.</p>
<p><em>So saida to Moyhammlet and marhaba to your Mount!</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 418)</p>
<p>Mohammed (McHugh 1980: 418), together with Zaida, forms another couple.
Together with the prophet comes the reference to the mountain (also suggested
by McHugh 1980: 418). Again the order is reversed (“to your Mount”); there is a
shift in power. <em>Saida</em> in Portuguese means an exit, a way out. Another
possibility of interpretation is reading “Moyhammlet” as Hamlet (McHugh 1980:
418), and again we enter a whole subtext of conflict between a (step)son and
(step)father. On the biblical level of interpretation we have <em>marhaba</em>, which is
Arabic with Aramaic roots. Incidentally, Aramaic is the original language of
several sections of the Bible, and also the language supposedly spoken by
Jesus. <em>Mar</em> means “God”; <em>haba</em> means “love”.</p>
<p><em>Let who likes lump above so what flies be a full’un;</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>:
418)</p>
<p>Flies continue the insect theme; simultaneously there is reference to a
universal order of things: as above, so below; to each his own.</p>
<p><em>I could not feel moregruggy if this was prompollen.</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 418)</p>
<p>Here, “moregruggy” again refers to an ant (McHugh 1980: 418), “prompollen” to a
beetle (ibid).</p>
<p><em>I pick up your reproof, the horsegift of a friend,</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 418)</p>
<p>On the plot level, read literally, the grasshopper takes the ant’s rebuke,
probably graciously (as the preceding and following lines suggest).
Additionally, this line evokes the proverb “never look a gift horse in the
mouth” (McHugh 1980: 418), and is also suggestive of the Trojan horse:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Equo ne credite, Teucri! Quidquid id est, timeo Danaos et dona ferentis. – “Do
not trust the horse, Trojans! Whatever it is, I fear the Danaans (Greeks), even
when they bring gifts”. (Virgil. “Aeneid II” 49) </p>
</blockquote>
<p>Joyce also alludes to Virgil in other parts of <em>Finnegans Wake</em>, and he is a
fitting travel companion here in the night and the underworld of HCE’s dreams,
since he is also Dante’s guide into hell in the <em>Inferno</em>.</p>
<p><em>For the prize of your save is the price of my spend.</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 418)</p>
<p>This line gives us a sense of order and justice. Literally read, it also brings
us back to the morale of  “The Ant and the Grasshopper”.</p>
<p><em>Can castwhores pulladeftkiss if oldpollocks forsake’em</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>:
418)</p>
<p>Another couple of twin brothers is alluded to here: Castor &amp; Pollux (McHugh
1980: 418), who remind us of the twins Shaun and Shem. “Forsake’em” continues
the biblical theme: <em>“Eli, Eli, lama sabachthani” – “My God, my God, why hast
thou forsaken me?”</em> (The King James Bible 2011: Matthew 27:46) are the last
words of Jesus on the cross to his father, and again they are in Aramaic.</p>
<p>Thus, also the father/son theme is continued (on another level: Shaun vs. HCE).</p>
<p>Literally, rhetorically, the grasshopper is defending himself, as continued in
the following line:</p>
<p><em>Or Culex feel etchy if Pulex don’t wake him?</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 418)</p>
<p>More insects: <em>Culex</em> is a gnat, <em>pulex</em> a flea; “etchy” can be read as “itchy”
(McHugh 1980: 418).</p>
<p>The Gracehoper continues his defence (using a rhetorical question, its meaning
along the lines of “I can’t help it; it's in my nature”) and implicitly appeals
to the Ondt for mercy (as in the fable).</p>
<p><em>A locus to loue, a term it t’embarrass,</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 418)</p>
<p>The Grasshopper’s plea: “A locust” (McHugh 1980: 418) - referring to himself -
“to love; a termite to embrace” (ibid). The abbreviated “t’” in “t’embarrass” is
suggestive of a different abbreviation in French: (je) t’embrace. At the same
time, “a term it t’embarrass” is very close to “(even) a termite would be
embarrassed”, again an appeal to the Ant.</p>
<p><em>These twain are the twins that tick Homo Vulgaris.</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 418)</p>
<p>The twins are mentioned again, as if he was saying that brothers belong
together.</p>
<p>“Tick” can refer to both the animal (McHugh 1980: 418) and time (another theme
which is going to be continued).</p>
<p>The Gracehoper’s entreaty: all insects are equal; difference is not the way
out.</p>
<p>All of the following rhetorical questions also reinforce the point the
Grasshopper is making:</p>
<p><em>Has Aquileone nort winged to go syf Since the Gwyffyn we were in his farthest
drewbryf And that Accident Man not beseeched where his story ends Since
longsephyring sighs sought heartseast for their orience?</em>  (Joyce. <em>Finnegans
Wake</em>: 418)</p>
<p>In addition we have a sense of direction, spanning the whole world: north,
south, occident, orient.</p>
<p>“Gwyffin” denotes a griffin, “drewbryf” a drawbridge (McHugh1980: 418).</p>
<p>(Not) <em>besiegt</em> literally means (not!) conquered (McHugh 1980: 418), but (with
the drawbridge up) can also be “besieged” (cf. the Trojan war and the
“horsegift”). If we read “beseeched”, though, as literally in the text, we
remain with the Gracehoper’s plea. This also fits the “longsephyring” that can
be picked apart into “longsuffering” and “zephyrs” (McHugh 1980: 418).</p>
<p>Finally, there is the theme of time and death again: “where his story ends”;
and “heartseast“, homophonous with ”heart ceased”.</p>
<p><em>We are Wastenot with Want, precondamned, two and true,</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>:
418)</p>
<p>Another idiom: “Waste not, want not” (McHugh 1980: 418), and also some of the
recurring religious motives: “(pre-)condemned” and “damned” allude to hell
again, and also to original sin and to the Fall of Lucifer (Milton again, and
the uprising against a tyrannical father figure).</p>
<p><em>Till Nolans go volants and Bruneyes come blue.</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 418)</p>
<p><em>Nolens volens</em> means “willy nilly” (McHugh 1980: 418). In accordance with the
preceding line, order has again changed to chaos. There is also a notion of
time: “Till Nolans go volants” (possibly French for “flying”) “and Bruneyes
come blue” sounds nonsensical (especially if you read “brown eyes” for
“Bruneyes”), which could mean something like “till the end of the world /
doomsday”. It is also reminiscent of the (seemingly nonsensical, or at least
wildly improbable) prophecy in Macbeth: <em>Till Birnam Wood remove to Dunsinane</em>
(Shakespeare. The Tragedy of Macbeth I:III:2).</p>
<p>An additional meta-reference is evoked, too: The “Nolans” in combination with
the “Bruneyes” remind one of Giordano Bruno (of Nola) whose theories, together
with those of Giambattista Vico, support a lot of the structure of <em>Finnegans
Wake</em> (cf. Füger 1994: 267f). In this case it might reinforce the Grasshopper’s
plea for confraternity: <em>every power in nature must evolve an opposite in order
to realize itself and opposition brings reunion</em> (Bruno, quoted in Füger 1994:
268).</p>
<p><em>Ere those gidflirts now gadding you quit your mocks for my gropes</em> (Joyce.
<em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 418)</p>
<p>More insects: “Gidflirts” shifts to gadflies (McHugh 1980: 418). There is also
an allusion to the Mookse and the Gripes (ibid), another passage in <em>Finnegans
Wake</em> (Joyce: <em>Finnegans Wake</em> 152ff), which opens up a whole new level of meta-
and subtext, since it contains overt references to Joyce himself and his
writing of <em>Finnegans Wake</em>.</p>
<p><em>“[…] you quit your mocks for my gropes”</em>: Is the Gracehoper still pleading, or
is he now threatening the Ondt? He seems to be mentioning a deadline, too, but
that could also refer to the approach of winter.</p>
<p><em>An extense must impull, an elapse must elopes,</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 418)</p>
<p>One more reference to order and dependency: “an elapse” (time) “must elopes”
(not time; an exit) – either “time flies” (if we are talking about linear
time), or not at all (“elopes”, cyclical / non-linear time).</p>
<p><em>Of my tectucs takestock, tinktact, and ail’s weal</em>; (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 418)</p>
<p>“Of my tactics take stock” (McHugh 1980: 418); “tic tac”, “all’s well” (ibid) –
which can be continued with “that ends well”, another Shakespeare reference,
and again an end.</p>
<p>“Ail” (pain) becomes “weal” (happiness, prosperity, welfare) – if the Ondt
gives in.</p>
<p>The rhythm and alliterative repetitions mimic the ticking of a clock as well.</p>
<p><em>As I view by your farlook hale yourself to my heal.</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>:
418)</p>
<p>“Hale” and “heal” go well with the “all’s well” from above; while “to my heel”
suggests another plea: “follow me; we belong together” (cf. the twins). This
notion of sharing is also illustrated in the following lines:</p>
<p><em>Partiprise my thinwhins whiles my blink points unbroken on
Your whole’s whereabroads with Tout’s trightyright token on.</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans
Wake</em>: 419)</p>
<p>In addition, “whiles” can also mean time (linear as well as non-linear: an
expanse of time, or simultaneity). A tout is a solicitor or barker.</p>
<p><em>My in risible universe youdly haud find
Sulch oxtrabeeforeness meat soveal behind.</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 419)</p>
<p>“In risible” contains “invisible” and, simultaneously, laughter (McHugh 1980:
419) - but separated, thus already implying a possible negation. There is also
a reference to Aristotle and Aquinas’ “visible universe” (McHugh 1980: 419) –
but at the same time “invisible” suggests things behind things (cf. mysticism).
The next line contains “ox”, “beef”, “meat”, “veal” (McHugh 1980: 419), but
also <em>“mit soviel”</em>+”behind” – s. above.</p>
<p><em>Your feats end enormous, your volumes immense,</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 419)</p>
<p>Again, an “end” of sorts, and in “your volumes immense” a possible allusion to
all the cultural/literary references in the text (and possible hidden meanings
alluded to in the previous line).</p>
<p><em>(May the Graces I hoped for sing your Ondtship song sense!),</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans
Wake</em>: 419)</p>
<p>Again, the Gracehoper is referring to himself and his name. The Graces he hopes
for are obviously personified in this line, referring to the Greek Graces, the
goddesses of charm, beauty and creativity. “Sing your song sense” might mean
that the seemingly opaque text needs to be decoded in order to make sense, to
give up its hidden meaning(s), as mentioned above.</p>
<p><em>Your genus its worldwide, your spacest sublime!</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 419)</p>
<p>Here, “spacest” might (also) translate to “species” (McHugh 1980: 419).</p>
<p><em>But, Holy Saltmartin, why can’t you beat time?</em> (Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 419)</p>
<p>“Saltmartin” can mean both St Martin and another insect (McHugh 1980: 419).</p>
<p>The imploring “why can’t you beat time?” might (among other things) be a
reference to the song (the ballad) and its rhythm. Re-establishing the theme of
time, it might also imply that the Ondt can’t “beat time”, can’t escape linear
time. It is always planning ahead (cf. the fable), remaining in linear time; it
symbolizes the worker and also stands in for the postman. The Gracehoper on the
other hand, the penman, the artist, spends his life outside linear time (in
elysium, in cyclical time). As in the original fable, the ant is slave to time,
while the grasshopper is simply not concerned.</p>
<p>Finally, in the following paragraph, Joyce uses a (version of a) formula that
not only symbolizes another ending but also adds a sort of morale, like a fable
should have:</p>
<p><em>In the name of the former and of the latter and of their holocaust. Allmen</em>
(Joyce. <em>Finnegans Wake</em>: 419).</p>
<p>The terms “former” and “latter” (apart from referring to the father as the one
who came before and the son as the one to later take his place, also cf. Shaun
&amp; HCE) only make sense in relation to time.</p>
<p>“Holocaust” means: an end to that. There is also the obvious allusion to death.</p>
<p>In this context, apart from the obvious <em>amen</em>, “all men” might mean: may
all men be liberated from linear time (and “saved” in the religious sense:
attain grace).</p>
<p><em>Finnegans Wake</em> doesn’t have a beginning or end. It begins and ends in
mid-sentence, thus forming an endless cycle. Every re-reading will inevitably
be different, both because of the previous knowledge of the text as such, and
because of a difference in background knowledge and a multitude of personal
factors that might have changed since the last reading. This, together with
Joyce’s abundant use of generators, of portmanteau words and neologisms (as
shown above), makes the novel an interesting and fecund text for possible
interpretation, and also for finding out more about different processes of
reading and interpretation and about the readers’ minds. It is therefore
necessary not to stipulate a concept of an “ideal reader” or of a “right way”
to interpret anything about it, but rather to approach it with an open mind,
and to engage in playful interaction with the text.</p>
<p>My interpretation of the Gracehoper’s ballad from “The Ant and the
Grasshopper” is and can only be one of a seemingly endless number of possible
readings, a recording of a moment in time. The next time I read this passage,
it will already have shifted, maybe acquired new meanings, maybe lost a few of
the ones I saw before. It has already expanded since the first time I read the
text, and I expect it to undergo many more transformations.</p>
<p>In this way, I hope I have succeeded in providing a plausible example of
how <em>Finnegans Wake</em> works, what it does to the reader, and what results from
creative interaction with the text. I think the best way to describe it in only
a couple of words is - like the novel, and even the title itself - because of
its inherent ambiguity more than the seeming paradox one might see, and
hopefully transcending it: Constant / Change. </p>
<h2>References</h2>
<h3>Primary Sources</h3>
<p>Anonymous (19th Century). “Finnegan’s Wake”. [Online] Western Michigan
University. <a href="http://homepages.wmich.edu/~cooneys/poems/fwake.html">http://homepages.wmich.edu/~cooneys/poems/fwake.html</a> [2011, April
20].</p>
<p>Jacobs, Joseph (ed, 1894). The Fables of Aesop. London: Macmillan.</p>
<p>Joyce, James (1992/2000). Finnegans Wake [1939]. Introd. S. Deane. Modern
Classics. London: Penguin.</p>
<p>Milton, John (1674). “Paradise Lost”. [Online] Dartmouth Milton Reading Room.
<a href="http://www.dartmouth.edu/~milton/reading_room/pl/book_1/index.shtml">http://www.dartmouth.edu/~milton/reading_room/pl/book_1/index.shtml</a> [2011,
April 20].</p>
<p>Shakespeare, William (1997). The Tragedy of Macbeth [1606]. In: The Complete
Works of William Shakespeare. [Online] Project Gutenberg.
<a href="http://www.gutenberg.org/cache/epub/1129/pg1129.html">http://www.gutenberg.org/cache/epub/1129/pg1129.html</a> [2011, April 20].</p>
<p>“The Gospel According to Saint Matthew” (2011).The King James Bible [1611].
[Online] Project Gutenberg. 
<a href="http://www.gutenberg.org/files/10/10-h/10-h.htm#The_Gospel_According_to_Saint_Matthew">http://www.gutenberg.org/files/10/10-h/10-h.htm#The_Gospel_According_to_Saint_Matthew</a>
[2011, April 20].</p>
<p>Virgil (2008). “Aeneidos. Liber II”.[Online] Project Gutenberg.
<a href="http://www.gutenberg.org/files/227/227-h/227-h.htm#liber02">http://www.gutenberg.org/files/227/227-h/227-h.htm#liber02</a> [2011, April 20].</p>
<h3>Secondary Sources</h3>
<p>Campbell, Joseph and Henry M. Robinson (1944/1959). A Skeleton Key to
Finnegans Wake. London: Faber &amp; Faber.</p>
<p>Eco, Umberto (1973/1977). Das offene Kunstwerk. Frankfurt a.M.: Suhrkamp.</p>
<p>Füger, Wilhelm (1994). James Joyce. Epoche – Werk – Wirkung. München: C.H.
Beck.</p>
<p>Hill, J. (2010). “Horus the child”. [Online] Ancient Egypt Online. 
<a href="http://www.ancientegyptonline.co.uk/horuschild.html">http://www.ancientegyptonline.co.uk/horuschild.html</a> [2011, April 20].</p>
<p>Ito, Eishiro (2002). “In the buginning is the woid”. [Online] Atelier Aterui.
<a href="http://p-www.iwate-pu.ac.jp/~acro-ito/Joycean_Essays/FW414_buginning.html">http://p-www.iwate-pu.ac.jp/~acro-ito/Joycean_Essays/FW414_buginning.html</a>
[2011, April 26].</p>
<p>Keiper, Hugo (2008).”’It's a hard egg’: Mondegreens and other (mis)construals
of pop lyrics – and what they can teach us” [2008]. In: Nada Šabec.
Literature and Culture in a Global Context. Ed. English Language. Zora 57.
Maribor: 32-45.</p>
<p>McHugh, Roland (1980). Annotations to Finnegans Wake. London: Routledge.</p>
<p>Miéville, China (2011). “The Weird: a discussion of fiction and politics with
China Miéville”. [Online] Backdoor Broadcasting Company.
<a href="http://backdoorbroadcasting.net/2011/03/the-weird-a-discussion-of-fiction-and-politics-with-china-mieville">http://backdoorbroadcasting.net/2011/03/the-weird-a-discussion-of-fiction-and-politics-with-china-mieville</a>
[2011, March 5].</p>
<p>Reichert, Klaus (1989). Vielfacher Schriftsinn. Zu Finnegans Wake. Frankfurt
a.M.: Suhrkamp.</p></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>dreamers.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2013/07/03/01-dreamers.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2013-07-03:2013/07/03/dreamers</id>
        <updated>2013-07-03T15:39:22Z</updated>
        <published>2013-07-03T15:39:17Z</published>
        <category term="music"/><category term="bars"/><category term="restaurants"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I've recently returned from a one week vacation in
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imperia">Imperia</a>, Italy. While the vacation
in total was very nice, I want to highlight one particular experience,
namely a bar that I've decided to put on my personal list-of-coolest-bars.</p>
<p>It is called <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/The-Dreamers-I-Sognatori/290877780949971?_fb_noscript=1">The
Dreamers</a>
(warning, link goes to Facebook) and is located in Borgo Foce, Porto
Maurizio, Imperia.</p>
<p>Why is it cool?</p>
<ul>
<li>it is directly by the sea</li>
<li>drinks are cheap(ish)</li>
<li>there is a free(!) buffet of good food</li>
<li>the barkeeper looks like Robert Downey Jr (no really) (no I didn't take
a picture)</li>
</ul></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>arp2.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2013/06/11/01-arp2.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2013-06-11:2013/06/11/arp2</id>
        <updated>2013-06-11T23:55:27Z</updated>
        <published>2013-06-11T23:53:13Z</published>
        <category term="computers"/><category term="networking"/><category term="android"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>So.</p>
<p>The problem is reproducible. Was online in the wifi where server is
reachable directly, server went into arp cache. Disconnected from said
wifi, connected to other wifi. Server still in arp cache, now as </p>
<div class="codehilite"><pre><span/>&lt;incomplete&gt; on wlan0
</pre></div>
<p>and therefore, again, unreachable under that IP address.</p>
<p>So at least on this Droid4, arp cache handling is definitely b0rken.</p>
<p>Note: if anyone else can reproduce this, I'd be happy to hear about it.</p></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>arp.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2013/06/10/01-arp.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2013-06-10:2013/06/10/arp</id>
        <updated>2013-06-11T23:57:56Z</updated>
        <published>2013-06-10T11:17:19Z</published>
        <category term="computers"/><category term="networking"/><category term="android"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>So I've stumbled across this weird networking issue while using my Android
phone (a rooted Droid 4). What I was seeing was this:</p>
<p>I had gone to our <a href="http://www.in-ulm.de">club</a> hangout and had used the
wifi there. After coming back home again, and using my wifi at home, my
phone wouldn't connect to my server, neither via SSH nor via IMAPS nor any
other protocol. Fearing something had caused my server to go offline, I
tried to reach it in other ways (i.e. by connecting through other hosts).</p>
<p>I then discovered something weird.</p>
<ul>
<li>my server <em>was</em> online</li>
<li>I could connect to it via some other remote host that took a different
 path into the server network</li>
<li>oh wait, I could connect to it via a different host that was in the same
 network as my server? (Meaning the network as such was reachable)</li>
<li>oh wait, other computers <em>inside my wifi</em> can connect to the server? Uh
 .. what?</li>
<li>oh wait, when I disconnect from my wifi and use the 3G connection
 instead, I <em>can</em> connect to the server</li>
</ul>
<p>So, next, I looked at the shell on my phone again and tried to see if
maybe the routing was broken, but </p>
<div class="codehilite"><pre><span/>$ ip route show
</pre></div>
<p>gave a completely normal output (i.e. there was only the default route to
my wifi router plus the local netmask). Next, I tried to see whether there
was a pattern to to the IP addresses I could reach and the ones I
couldn't. There was. It was <em>only</em> the IP address of my server that was
unreachable. I tried connecting to the IP addresses of some VMs that run
<em>on that server</em> (i.e. behind the same bridging interface) and they were
reachable.</p>
<p>Just for laughs, I used another IP address from the same server network
that was unused at that time and added that one to the interface, and
my server was instantly reachable via that address. So it really was that
one, specific, IP address that was unreachable.</p>
<p>At which point a colleague of mine (I had thrown my story out to some
people I know to aid in brainstorming) said "Have you looked at the arp
cache?"</p>
<p>I hadn't.</p>
<p>So I did.</p>
<div class="codehilite"><pre><span/>$ arp
fnanp.in-ulm.n-addr.arpa <span class="o">(</span><span class="m">217</span>.10.9.38<span class="o">)</span> at &lt;incomplete&gt; on wlan0
</pre></div>
<p>So. A full two days earlier, my phone had been connected to a wifi in
which said server can be reached without going through a router and
therefore had added the servers address to its arp cache. If I read the
arp(7) manpage correctly, the lifetime of an entry in the arp cache should
be around the 30 seconds mark, but at this point it was already 48 hours
that it had been there. Another way to see that the phone thought the
server should be in the same network:</p>
<div class="codehilite"><pre><span/>$ ip neigh show
<span class="m">217</span>.10.9.38 dev wlan0 FAILED
</pre></div>
<p>also</p>
<div class="codehilite"><pre><span/>$ ip route show cache <span class="p">|</span> grep <span class="m">217</span>.10.9.38
</pre></div>
<p>showed it as a local address that was offline. At this point I was
pondering whether I should flush the cache and just be done with it or
whether I wanted to find out more about this. But then my parents came
over to visit and we went out to have dinner. When we came back and my
phone reconnected to my wifi, the issue was gone.</p>
<p>Well, I'll be back in the wifi that caused the whole problem tomorrow
evening. I'm curious whether it'll happen again.</p></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>defrage.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2013/06/09/02-defrage.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2013-06-09:2013/06/09/defrage</id>
        <updated>2013-06-09T15:21:39Z</updated>
        <published>2013-06-09T15:15:22Z</published>
        <category term="music"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>This is the story of how I met a member of the Band
<a href="https://de-de.facebook.com/defragemusic">Defrage</a> (warning: link goes to
Facebook).</p>
<p>I was at a petrol station near <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Innsbruck">Innsbruck,
Austria</a>, filling up the tank of
my car, when a young man carrying a plastic bag approached me and asked me
whether I spoke English. Assuming he wanted to ask for directions, I said
yes. He then wanted to know whether I liked music (a quite generic
question, but whatever). A bit unsure where that conversation was heading,
I answered yes again.</p>
<p>He then proceeded to tell me that he was in a band from
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Estonia">Estonia</a> and wanted to know what
<em>kind</em> of music I liked. Since I wanted to give the shortest possible
answer I said "Metal". At which point he pulled a cardboard cd-sleeve out
of his plastic bag, turned it around and pointed at a track-title marked
there which said "We Are Metal" and explained that, in fact, his band
<em>was</em> a Metal band. He then told me that his band was right now on tour
through Europe and was going to play at <a href="http://www.novarock.at">Nova
Rock</a> in a short while, but since they were a
young band without big resources, they were trying to finance their
touring by selling CDs to people and hey, would I maybe be interested in
purchasing a CD from him? Only EUR 15!</p>
<p>Now, on the one hand, stories that start with "I met this guy at a petrol
station/highway rest area, and he sold me X" are usually tales of how
somebody was conned into buying something utterly worthless or maybe even
an empty package. On the other hand, I liked his main argument ("if we
ever become famous, you'll be able to sell it on ebay for a million!"). So
I thought what the hell, gave him EUR 15 and received a shrink-wrapped
cardboard CD sleeve. He thanked me and then turned his attention onto
another prospective customer (and I saw that a colleague of his was busy
trying the same approach on a young lady at the next pump).</p>
<p>Getting into my car, I remarked to my wife that I was curious to find out
whether there actually <em>was</em> a CD in the sleeve at all.</p>
<p>And there was.</p>
<p>And bloody hell does it sound great!</p>
<p>I would describe the sound as sortof <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fear_Factory">Fear
Factory</a> during the
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Obsolete_(album)">Obsolete</a>
era (which, to me, equals "brilliant!"). Apparently, the CDs are not
available for sale through normal channels but the band seems to be quite
busy using their unique sales approach in parking lots/fastfood
restaurants/pedestrian areas in Austria/Bavaria/Switzerland. So if you
happen to meet them, definitely buy that CD!</p>
<p>5 out of 5 stars!</p></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>first post on the new klo.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2013/06/09/01-first_post_on_the_new_klo.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2013-06-09:2013/06/09/first_post_on_the_new_klo</id>
        <updated>2013-06-09T10:42:18Z</updated>
        <published>2013-06-09T10:42:11Z</published>
        <category term="administrativa"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Ich gebe zu, den Titel kapieren jetzt hoechstens 10 Leute, und maximal 2
von denen werden das hier lesen, aber SCNR.</p>
<p>Jedenfalls: hin und wieder kann es vorkommen, dass ich der Welt was
mitteilen will, was nicht ins
<a href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/frederik_und_moritz/sbe/">Kinderblog</a> passt, und
was ausserdem zu viel Text fuer <a href="https://twitter.com/das_aug">Twitter</a>
ist. Dafuer soll jetzt dieses Theater hier gut sein.</p></div></content>
    </entry>
</feed>