<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>ein Blog</title>
    <id>http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/</id>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog" type="text/html"/>
    <link rel="self" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/atom.xml" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <updated>2013-06-11T23:58:06Z</updated>
    <entry>
        <title>arp2.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2013/06/11/01-arp2.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2013-06-11:2013/06/11/arp2</id>
        <updated>2013-06-11T23:55:27Z</updated>
        <published>2013-06-11T23:53:13Z</published>
        <category term="computers"/><category term="networking"/><category term="android"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>So.</p>
<p>The problem is reproducible. Was online in the wifi where server is
reachable directly, server went into arp cache. Disconnected from said
wifi, connected to other wifi. Server still in arp cache, now as </p>
<pre class="codehilite"><code>&lt;incomplete&gt; on wlan0</code></pre>
<p>and therefore, again, unreachable under that IP address.</p>
<p>So at least on this Droid4, arp cache handling is definitely b0rken.</p>
<p>Note: if anyone else can reproduce this, I'd be happy to hear about it.</p></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>arp.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2013/06/10/01-arp.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2013-06-10:2013/06/10/arp</id>
        <updated>2013-06-11T23:57:56Z</updated>
        <published>2013-06-10T11:17:19Z</published>
        <category term="computers"/><category term="networking"/><category term="android"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>So I've stumbled across this weird networking issue while using my Android
phone (a rooted Droid 4). What I was seeing was this:</p>
<p>I had gone to our <a href="http://www.in-ulm.de">club</a> hangout and had used the
wifi there. After coming back home again, and using my wifi at home, my
phone wouldn't connect to my server, neither via SSH nor via IMAPS nor any
other protocol. Fearing something had caused my server to go offline, I
tried to reach it in other ways (i.e. by connecting through other hosts).</p>
<p>I then discovered something weird.</p>
<ul>
<li>my server <em>was</em> online</li>
<li>I could connect to it via some other remote host that took a different
 path into the server network</li>
<li>oh wait, I could connect to it via a different host that was in the same
 network as my server? (Meaning the network as such was reachable)</li>
<li>oh wait, other computers <em>inside my wifi</em> can connect to the server? Uh
 .. what?</li>
<li>oh wait, when I disconnect from my wifi and use the 3G connection
 instead, I <em>can</em> connect to the server</li>
</ul>
<p>So, next, I looked at the shell on my phone again and tried to see if
maybe the routing was broken, but </p>
<pre class="codehilite"><code>$ ip route show</code></pre>
<p>gave a completely normal output (i.e. there was only the default route to
my wifi router plus the local netmask). Next, I tried to see whether there
was a pattern to to the IP addresses I could reach and the ones I
couldn't. There was. It was <em>only</em> the IP address of my server that was
unreachable. I tried connecting to the IP addresses of some VMs that run
<em>on that server</em> (i.e. behind the same bridging interface) and they were
reachable.</p>
<p>Just for laughs, I used another IP address from the same server network
that was unused at that time and added that one to the interface, and
my server was instantly reachable via that address. So it really was that
one, specific, IP address that was unreachable.</p>
<p>At which point a colleague of mine (I had thrown my story out to some
people I know to aid in brainstorming) said "Have you looked at the arp
cache?"</p>
<p>I hadn't.</p>
<p>So I did.</p>
<pre class="codehilite"><code>$ arp
fnanp.in-ulm.n-addr.arpa (217.10.9.38) at &lt;incomplete&gt; on wlan0</code></pre>
<p>So. A full two days earlier, my phone had been connected to a wifi in
which said server can be reached without going through a router and
therefore had added the servers address to its arp cache. If I read the
arp(7) manpage correctly, the lifetime of an entry in the arp cache should
be around the 30 seconds mark, but at this point it was already 48 hours
that it had been there. Another way to see that the phone thought the
server should be in the same network:</p>
<pre class="codehilite"><code>$ ip neigh show
217.10.9.38 dev wlan0 FAILED</code></pre>
<p>also</p>
<pre class="codehilite"><code>$ ip route show cache | grep 217.10.9.38</code></pre>
<p>showed it as a local address that was offline. At this point I was
pondering whether I should flush the cache and just be done with it or
whether I wanted to find out more about this. But then my parents came
over to visit and we went out to have dinner. When we came back and my
phone reconnected to my wifi, the issue was gone.</p>
<p>Well, I'll be back in the wifi that caused the whole problem tomorrow
evening. I'm curious whether it'll happen again.</p></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>defrage.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2013/06/09/02-defrage.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2013-06-09:2013/06/09/defrage</id>
        <updated>2013-06-09T15:21:39Z</updated>
        <published>2013-06-09T15:15:22Z</published>
        <category term="music"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>This is the story of how I met a member of the Band
<a href="https://de-de.facebook.com/defragemusic">Defrage</a> (warning: link goes to
Facebook).</p>
<p>I was at a petrol station near <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Innsbruck">Innsbruck,
Austria</a>, filling up the tank of
my car, when a young man carrying a plastic bag approached me and asked me
whether I spoke English. Assuming he wanted to ask for directions, I said
yes. He then wanted to know whether I liked music (a quite generic
question, but whatever). A bit unsure where that conversation was heading,
I answered yes again.</p>
<p>He then proceeded to tell me that he was in a band from
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Estonia">Estonia</a> and wanted to know what
<em>kind</em> of music I liked. Since I wanted to give the shortest possible
answer I said "Metal". At which point he pulled a cardboard cd-sleeve out
of his plastic bag, turned it around and pointed at a track-title marked
there which said "We Are Metal" and explained that, in fact, his band
<em>was</em> a Metal band. He then told me that his band was right now on tour
through Europe and was going to play at <a href="http://www.novarock.at">Nova
Rock</a> in a short while, but since they were a
young band without big resources, they were trying to finance their
touring by selling CDs to people and hey, would I maybe be interested in
purchasing a CD from him? Only EUR 15!</p>
<p>Now, on the one hand, stories that start with "I met this guy at a petrol
station/highway rest area, and he sold me X" are usually tales of how
somebody was conned into buying something utterly worthless or maybe even
an empty package. On the other hand, I liked his main argument ("if we
ever become famous, you'll be able to sell it on ebay for a million!"). So
I thought what the hell, gave him EUR 15 and received a shrink-wrapped
cardboard CD sleeve. He thanked me and then turned his attention onto
another prospective customer (and I saw that a colleague of his was busy
trying the same approach on a young lady at the next pump).</p>
<p>Getting into my car, I remarked to my wife that I was curious to find out
whether there actually <em>was</em> a CD in the sleeve at all.</p>
<p>And there was.</p>
<p>And bloody hell does it sound great!</p>
<p>I would describe the sound as sortof <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fear_Factory">Fear
Factory</a> during the
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Obsolete_(album)">Obsolete</a>
era (which, to me, equals "brilliant!"). Apparently, the CDs are not
available for sale through normal channels but the band seems to be quite
busy using their unique sales approach in parking lots/fastfood
restaurants/pedestrian areas in Austria/Bavaria/Switzerland. So if you
happen to meet them, definitely buy that CD!</p>
<p>5 out of 5 stars!</p></div></content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title>first post on the new klo.</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/blog/2013/06/09/01-first_post_on_the_new_klo.html" type="text/html"/>
        <id>tag:fnanp.in-ulm.de,2013-06-09:2013/06/09/first_post_on_the_new_klo</id>
        <updated>2013-06-09T10:42:18Z</updated>
        <published>2013-06-09T10:42:11Z</published>
        <category term="administrativa"/>
        <author>
            <name>michael</name>
        </author>
        <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Ich gebe zu, den Titel kapieren jetzt hoechstens 10 Leute, und maximal 2
von denen werden das hier lesen, aber SCNR.</p>
<p>Jedenfalls: hin und wieder kann es vorkommen, dass ich der Welt was
mitteilen will, was nicht ins
<a href="http://fnanp.in-ulm.de/frederik_und_moritz/sbe/">Kinderblog</a> passt, und
was ausserdem zu viel Text fuer <a href="https://twitter.com/das_aug">Twitter</a>
ist. Dafuer soll jetzt dieses Theater hier gut sein.</p></div></content>
    </entry>
</feed>